Finding Aid for P.S. Lovejoy Papers 1918-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
P.S. Lovejoy Papers 1918-1941
Lovejoy, Parrish Storrs, 1884-1992
5 linear feet
851738 Aa 2
Professor of forestry in the School of Natural Resources at the University of Michigan, active in conservation movement, first head of the Michigan Game Division and a popular writer on conservation topics; papers consist of correspondence (including Aldo Leopold and Gifford Pinchot and leading conservationists), reports, writings and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the School of Natural Resources of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1887 ).
The collection is open for research.
P.S. Lovejoy, professor in the School of Natural Resources of University of Michigan, was a significant figure in the history of Michigan conservation. From the Ann Arbor News, dated January 21, 1942, we can read this assessment. "From him came many of the ideas, many of the inspirations, many of the stimulations that have turned and are turning millions of acres of cutover, bankrupt, seemingly worthless lands in the north into game areas, new forest, and recreation places for the people."
Born January 23, 1884 in Princeton, Illinois, Lovejoy attended the University of Michigan from 1903 to 1907 and 1908 to 1909, but left without graduating to pursue a career in forestry. From 1907 to 1912, he held a series of increasingly responsible positions in the U.S. Forest Service, working in a wide variety of national forests: Hell Gate in Montana (1908), later Cheyenne N.F., Crow Creek N.F., Medicine Bow N.F., Olympic N.F (1910-1912). He then returned to the University of Michigan in 1912 when he received appointment as assistant professor of forestry.
Although Michigan was his adopted state, Lovejoy was particularly concerned about the state's land utilization. From 1919 to 1925, he was chairman of the conservation committee of the Michigan Academy of Science that met to discuss the state's wild land situation. Here was proposed a Land Economic Survey that Lovejoy was called upon to organize and staff. In 1925, Lovejoy undertook the establishment of game refuges and game preserves on a sound scientific basis. He then became the state's first chief of the Game Division. In 1930, he became chief advisor of the department on land policy and program, a position he held until his death in 1942.
Lovejoy was also a prolific writer on topics relating to forestry. In 1920, he had left the University to become a staff writer for the Curtis Publishing Company, publishers of The Country Gentleman, and The Saturday Evening Post.
Lovejoy died January 20, 1942.
The collection has been divided into four series: Papers, Articles and Related Material, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
The collection consists of five linear feet of correspondence and articles, and other materials relating to Lovejoy's work on behalf of forest conservation, forestry in general, his work with various state and local organizations, and his career as a writer for different national magazines.
Though the collection dates from 1918 to 1941, it bulks largest (except for the Articles series) in the period beginning in 1931. This was after Lovejoy had left the University of Michigan and after his pioneering work in the 1920s.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Forests and forestry--Michigan.; Michigan Farm Bureau.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Contributors:
Leopold, Aldo, 1886-1948.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.
Visual Materials - Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Alfalfa.; Farming.; Farms--Michigan.; Fences.; Forests.; Orchards.; Raspberries.
Form and Genre:
Photographs.
- Papers
  The Papers series includes a mixture of correspondence, reports, memoranda, drafts of various writings. The series The Papers series has been arranged chronologically. Among Lovejoy's correspondents were prominent figures of the conservation movement including Gifford Pinchot and Aldo Leopold. An index to the Leopold and Pincot correspondence appears at end of this finding aid.
  - Volume containing copies of correspondence exchanged between PSL and Aldo Leopold 1933-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1918-1924 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1937, 27 folders (Box 1)
  - 1937-1938, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - 1933-1938, 5 folders (Box 2)
    Miscellaneous
  - 1939, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1939-1941, 31 folders (Box 3)
    - Isle Royale (Davenport manuscript), 1940 (Box 3)
    - Bulletin production bottlenecks 1941 (Box 3)
    - Leopold, Aldo 1941 (Box 3)
    - Pittman-Robertson Report 1941 (Box 3)
    - Schoenmann, L.R. 1941 (Box 3)
    - Waterloo 1941 (Box 3)
- Articles and related material
  The Articles and Related Material series dates from 1921 to 1924 and includes drafts of articles written as well as some of the correspondence received in response to articles. This series also includes unpublished writings.
  - 1921
    - "Farmer and Forest Fight,"
      - Correspondence between Lovejoy and editor of Country Gentleman, 6 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence re. article, May-December, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - "Woodlot Problems,"
      - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence between Lovejoy and editor of Country Gentleman (Box 4)
      - Correspondence re. article
        - undated December 1921-February 1922 (Box 4)
        - March 1922-March 1923 (Box 4)
    - "Splitting the Department" (Box 4)
    - Building series, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - American Association of Nurserymen article, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan State Farm Bureau article, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1922
    - "Woodlot Taxation", 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "State Land Policy in Michigan" (Box 4)
      (unpublished paper)
    - Editorials in Country Gentleman (Box 4)
    - "State Fair Affairs" (Box 4)
    - "Present and Future Soil Surveys" (Box 4)
    - American Association of Nurserymen article, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Chicago Produce Market article (Box 5)
    - "Forestry in Michigan" (Box 5)
    - "Ecology and Economics of Forest Fires in Michigan" (Box 5)
    - "Good Seed and Tares" (Box 5)
    - "Taxes and County Business" (Box 5)
    - Land series, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - "A Bad Leak in Orcharding" (Box 5)
    - New York Produce Markets series (Box 5)
  - 1923
    - "Soil as Compared with Land Classification" (Box 5)
    - "What Junked Old Hort Mill" (Box 5)
    - "Is Uncle Sam Rich Enough to Give Us All a Farm?" (Box 5)
    - Raspberry disease article, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Alfalfa campaign article, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - "Why I'm Sore at Farmers" (Box 5)
    - "The Status of Lake State Forest Affairs" (Box 5)
    - Seed series, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - "In the Name of Development" (Box 5)
    - "Farm and Forest Development in the Cutover" (Box 5)
  - 1924
    - "Land Grab" editorial (Box 5)
    - Soil article (Box 5)
    - "Progress of the Land Economic Survey" (Box 5)
    - "Hijacking Among the Idle Lands" (Box 5)
    - Fence post article, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Undated
    - "Study of Spread of Forest Cover into Wild Land Openings" (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series consists of two folders, one of which is a chapter from a proposed history of game management.
  - History of Game Management (one chapter) (Box 5)
  - Game Protection Fund statistics (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists mainly of images used in articles written by Lovejoy on such topics as natural fencing construction, alfalfa and raspberry cultivation, forestry, and agriculture and the marketing of produce.
  - Photographs, 7 envelopes (Box 5)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Leopold, Aldo, 1886-1948
Aug. 17, 1936; Sept. 25, 1936; Oct. 21, 1936; Oct. 23, 1936; Dec. 22, 1936; Jan. 2, 1937; Feb. 3, 1937; Oct. 7, 1937; Nov. 2, 1937; Nov. 12, 1937; Feb. 26, 1938; April 25, 1939; Nov. 18, 1939; Aug. 26, 1940; Sept. 17, 1940; Sept. 26, 1940; and 1941 (individual folder)
Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946
July 2, 1940; and letters from "Farm and Forest Fight" file (Oct. 5, 1921; Nov. 18, 1921; Nov. 28, 1921; Dec. 12, 1921)